Register of the Austrian subject collection, 1893-1996
Hoover Institution Archives
Austrian Subject Collection,
1893-1996
XX749
6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 videotape cassette (3.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century Austrian history and politics, including the socialist revolt of 1934, the Anschluss of 1938, the anti-Nazi movement in Austria, post-World War II student radicalism at the Universitat Wien, the Austrian movement for European unity, and elections in Austria.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Anschluss movement, 1918-1938; Anti-Nazi movement; National socialism; Radicalism--Austria; Student movements--Austria; European federation; Austria; Austria--History--20th century; Austria--Politics and government--20th century; Socialism--Austria; Elections--Austria; Universitat Wien; Video tapes
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1867-1994. (Boxes 1-2)
  Leaflets, reports, programs, election and government literature relating to Austrian history and political life, arranged chronologically and then by subject
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1925. (Box 3)
  Financial reports and statements for fiscal year 1925 for the province of Kdrnten
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1867-1994
  - Miscellany. Bulletins, newsletters, and serial issues, l935-l954, issued by Austrian fascists before the Anschluss, and by anti-fascist Austrian emigres in Great Britain (Young Austria - Junges Oesterreich, Zeitspiegel - Weekly Review) and in France during World War II. Includes a certificate awarded to the New York Public Library by the Austrian Council for South Africa, l947, and typewritten compilation of information about the Austrian General Franz Conrad von Hoetzendorf, prepared by Dimitri Birkin, l954. In German and English (Box 1.)
  - 1867-1918. Pamphlets, newspaper and serial issues, reports, and resolutions, 1893-1914, issued by various socialist and workers' parties and associations. In German
  - 1918-1938
    - Anschluss, March 1938. Postage stamp issued in 1988 recalling the Anschluss of March 11
    - Dollfuss, Engelbert. Leaflet, l934, issued in commemoration of Engelbert Dollfuss, Chancellor of Austria, following his assassination during the Nazi Putsch of July 1934. In German
    - Plebiscite, April 1938
      - Ballot used in the April 10 plebiscite on the union with Germany. In German
      - Pamphlet by E. Muller-Sturmheim entitled 99.7%: A Plebiscite Under Nazi Rule, 1942
    - Socialist and communist opposition
      - General. Pamphlets published by the socialist and communist parties in the l930s, relating to their programs and to the anti-Nazi movement in Austria. In German
      - Revolt, February 1934
        - General. Broadsides, leaflets, and mimeographed articles primarily relating to the revolt of the social-democrats on February 12. In German
        - Schutzbund. Clippings from Austrian newspapers, l935, relating to the trial of leaders of the Schutzbund, the armed defense organization of the social democratic party, after the events of 1934. In German. Includes several issues of Kleines Volks-Zeitung, 1935
        - Underground literature. Socialist and communist underground leaflets, with camouflage covers, ca. l935-l936. In German
  - 1945-1955
    - Report of the United States Commissioner on the Military Government of Austria, November 1945
    - Issue of London-Information of the Austrian Socialists in Great Britain, 15 April 1946. In English
  - 1955-
    - Miscellany. Page from a newspaper issue, 1957, giving the words and music of the song "Lied der Arbeit." In German
    - Elections, 1988-1989. Election campaign literature and leaflets related to Austrian politics. In German
    - European Federation - Referendum, 1994. Pamphlets, serial issues, declarations, press releases, and position statements. In German and English
      - Freiheitliche Partei Oesterreichs. Party platform
      - Government publications (Chancellor's office) (Box 2.)
        - General
        - Economy and banking
        - Education
        - Environment
        - Foreign policy
        - Social policy
      - Maastricht treaty, February 7, 1992. In German
    - Kreisky, Bruno. Flyer issued by the Sozialistischer Jugendrat announcing a meeting with Bruno Kreisky to celebrate Austrian minorities, 18 March 1988. In German
    - Left wing movement. Brochures, circulars, flyers, magazine and newspaper issues, and stickers, 1992. Includes material from May 1 celebration. In German
    - Student organizations. Leaflets, periodicals, handwritten posters, and other miscellaneous materials, l970-l97l, distributed at the University of Vienna and relating primarily to the Osterreichische Studentenunion (Austrian Student Union) and university reform. In German
    - Waldheim, Kurt. Flyer and sticker relating to an anti-Waldheim demonstration held in February 1988. In German
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL.
  - Financial reports and statements for fiscal year 1925 for the province of Karnten (Box 3.)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 4-7)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.